hello Traders and welcome to the second
part of the technical analysis Mastery
Series in which I'm gonna teach you how
to analyze Market structure like a pro
so if you don't know how to draw Market
structure how to do it what is Major
structure what is minor structure how to
draw your Fibonacci ranges how to
differentiate between the different time
frames and everything in this video I'm
gonna try to make it all clear for you
by teaching you basic Market structure
at first then we're gonna jump onto some
more advanced Market structure Concepts
so that when you really put them
together you're gonna gain a deeper
understanding of Market structure
because in my opinion this is the
absolute Foundation of every single
strategy and again there are multiple
ways to be looking at Market structure
right this is how I personally do it so
if you can get something from me get
something from somebody else and then
build up your own trading strategy then
this is all I need to hear all right
again this is the second part of the
technical analysis Master Series so make
sure to go in the description and click
click on the link down there so you are
actually going to download your plan and
together with this I am gonna send you
some more PDFs from this lesson as well
so make sure to also re-watch the first
video which is the trading plan Series
right if you haven't built up your
trading plan you definitely must do so
right now so check the link in the
description get your plan build it and
right now it's time for some technical
knowledge so let's get into it
thank you
all right we're gonna get started with
an introduction to Market structure and
Trend identification which is pretty
much the foundation of your technical
analysis strategy you've probably heard
a lot of people say I'm a price action
Trader right but again what does price
action exactly mean let's have a look so
pretty much price action is when people
come together and they agree on a price
but that is on a massive scale right so
there is a constant decision process
between what is expensive and what is
cheap right so the market goes up the
market goes down right this is expensive
the market goes down this is cheap the
market goes up right pretty much there
is that constant battle between buyers
and sellers between supply and demand
right and there is nothing else we only
have buy orders in the market and we
only have sell orders in the market when
they are equal we have consolidation
When Buyers are more we have uptrend
when sellers are more we have downtrend
right and usually once again the
majority will always win what I truly
believe is that the bfis I call them the
BFI so banks financial institutions
hedge funds Pension funds all of those
guys right that actually control the
market right they simply have control
right and they make the decision on the
price right so the bfis have lots of
money so they can easily move they can
easily manipulate the market and they
decide what is going on us as retail
Traders we have no control over the
market moves right even if you trade a
hundred Lots even if you trade a
thousand Lots still you do not move the
market we are just little ants we're
just little dots in the grand scheme of
things right so what our aim is is to
understand how those big financial
institutions operate and simply follow
their Footprints right because they
always leave Footprints behind their
transactions they cannot hide where they
push the marketing right and this is why
I believe price action and Market
structure is actually what tells us
where the bfis are going right
and pretty much your chart is a visual
representation of the transactions and
the ending price at specific dates hours
minutes seconds price is always going to
be the same different time frames are
just going to represent price in
different ways so if you are on the
weekly time frame you're not going to
have a lot of details but if you go from
the weekly to the 50 minute oh you're
gonna have a lot more candles a lot more
details a lot more fluctuations right
but still price is the same
right so it went in the same way
shifting between time frames just
provides you with a little bit more
clarity on what exactly happened
and pretty much price action again the
candles and the transactions will build
Market structure patterns and footprints
on our charts and I want to give you an
example I'm just gonna do do so I want
you to think of it as a painting right
so you have a blank canvas and then
price action is the brush and die and of
course when you take this blank canvas
and put price action on it then your
final result is a chart with Market
structure with patterns with
candlesticks right and then if I ask you
who is the painter if you paid attention
then of course it's the bfis they paint
the market for us so if you understand
what is price action this is gonna put
you way ahead
over the majority of all the Traders
right so let me give an example
there's our blank canvas right so this
is just the chart but nothing right
what is this well this is price action
there are the candles there are the
moves there are the fluctuations the
market started with going down it
Consolidated and then started going up
right so this is pretty much how the
market moves
and then this is just raw data then what
you can do is you add Market structure
to it right to start marking lower highs
lower lows you start following the flow
then you spot the reversal patterns then
you spot the consolidation as well and
you just keep following the structure so
this is Market structure what is even
more powerful is when you add supply and
demand to it right so where are those
points of interest where are you going
to be entering from where is really
Supply kicking in where is the man
kicking in what is a good entry area
that you can look to get involved into
trade right and this is what really
builds everything so this is price
action trading but pretty much how I
trade personally is I'm a master at
Market structure I have combined it with
supply and demand I have a very clean
entry system and this is all you need
right and guys tell me please does this
look good or does this look better
right so again we don't want to be way
too over complicated and give you lots
of trend lines lots of indicators and
lots of that stuff so again in this
lesson we're going to keep it simple
we're going to keep it clean and of
course powerful so
let's get into Market structure okay as
I keep saying Market structure is the
strongest Foundation of technical
analysis period it is the breathing
pattern of the market this is how it
breathes it goes up it takes a breath it
pulls back then it goes up again takes a
breath it pulls back okay so if you
pretty much understand the simplest yet
still the hardest concept of structure
which is pretty much Harlow's hard highs
lower lows lower highs this is
contributing to 80 and even more of your
profitability I promise right because in
the past I did not fully understand
Market structure or I understood it but
what is also very important I want you
to take note of this is that you have a
systematic way of marking Market
structure because you can be you can
always be also different you can see
okay this is my lower height this time
but then the next day you change your
lower high to something else right and
you constantly fluctuate between your
Market structure marking okay Market
structure also illustrates who is in
control right so if the market is buying
if the market is going up well buyers
are in control right but usually the
indicator
it does show you this but you're first
gonna see it in price and then the
indicator is going to reflect on what
the price did so in the indicators are
lagging
Market structures used to identify the
trend and major and minor structure
right so then if you start understanding
the the market structure across
different time frames this is a whole
new skill which we're going to cover
also for major in Mark and minor
structure so why is Market structure
better than anything else right why is
Market structure better than support and
resistance and like indicators and all
that stuff I am gonna show you later and
in fact I'm just gonna jump on a chart
right now and show you why first of all
Market structure is better than support
and resistance and trend lines
so I am right now on an empty chart
right and it's not empty there is
something on the left but what I'm just
simply going to do is I'm just gonna go
ahead and plot a couple of horizontal
lines there is one there is two there's
three there's four there's five and
maybe yeah let's keep it like this right
so what is this well we can say okay
those are support and resistance level
but that actually see something with
them no right but then if I start going
on the left well what you're gonna see
is the market rejecting from those
levels right look at that zone right
there look at the interactions right the
market came in reacted look at this
level right there the market tapped
massively reacted then the market came
in tap this one retested this one and
then went down right and I can keep
going on I can go on the left where we
don't have much data right there but you
can see in the past right here look at
this Zone the market tapped in beautiful
reaction wow that's a powerful
resistance level right there look at
this how the market consolids roughly
around this level right so is this
really subjective again this is is not
the right way to Mark to to Mark a
support and resistance but again you can
mark it anywhere and you can just go in
your chart and say okay this is
resistance support support resistance
support resistance right support and
then you just get 100 lines and you
really don't understand what is going on
okay trend lines
how do you draw trend lines right so if
I just stick right there with this so do
I draw a trend line like that
right it got broken the market still
went up okay then I drew it like this it
got broken the market still went up okay
then I drew it like that right the
market then does uh like the first step
and then the second one was supposed to
work but we broke down
right then from the upside how do I draw
it like this okay we broke out right so
cool I'm going to be looking for Longs
on the trendline retest the market went
down and made a new lower low okay and I
can give you many examples on this right
this just keeps happening right there is
an upward trend line the market broke
down then it just starts ranging and
you're like okay what should I do so
this is why I really believe that market
structure is the key and you don't need
supporter resistance you don't need
trend lines right now let's jump back
onto the theory to see how it's actually
done
so I want to ask you a question what are
the two ways that the market is moving
right so very simple in essence the
market is always buying going up or
selling going down there is never
Stillness except when we have closed
markets where we have like the spread
hours at midnight right then the market
could be still for a little bit but it's
still buying and selling institutions
even buy and sell during the weekends so
when you have Monday open sometimes you
have huge gaps right why are those gaps
is because there were orders being
transacted even during the weekend right
so usually again the market is either
doing one of two things it's out of
trending which could be uptrended
downtrend or it's either consolidating
which is pretty much ranging choppy
unclear price section and there is a
rule that I want you to remember the no
over complication rule so the first
thing that to ask yourself in the
morning we're gonna sit in your chart is
the market up down or sideways and
usually you can spot this within 15
seconds right because it usually just
makes sense right so
the market also moves in Cycles it
oscillates between the mean value of
fear and greed all right so pretty much
if I just take my my pen right now the
Mark is going to go up then it's gonna
go down
and it's going to go up it's gonna go
down right and pretty much it always
oscillates between a line and especially
the Forex Market because currencies
they're not like stocks that are usually
going over the long-term bullish right
currencies tend to consolidate overall
if you look at the macro time frame but
within those consolidations there are
multiple trends that you can be
capitalizing on okay so remember this
Market moves in Cycles it goes up for a
little bit shifts down goes down it
shifts up goes up maybe a little bit of
a consolidation goes down okay so always
remember this so are you ready to learn
how to identify structure let's have a
look this is going to be a basic
introduction of Market structure
again uptrend so what is an uptrend this
is defined as Market structure that is
breaking the highs and maintaining the
lows in simple terms a market that is
making hard highs and higher lows the
previous or last High which is the
higher high should always break while
the previous low which is the higher low
should not be broken and if I put an
example right there right to start with
a low
we make a high this low should not break
in order to maintain the uptrend right
but this high should always break in
order to maintain the uptrend right so
again the last heart high should always
break the previous high low should not
be broken okay and again we have a high
this is the new higher low it should not
break there is the new one what it
should do it should go and take out the
high so very simple and I'm sure you
notice again this is not uh this is more
like a textbook but what you're usually
going to have in the live market is
something like that right it's not
because you have a push the marketing
starts to chop around it gives you like
internal structure but water is really
important is that you always track the
market down to spot like what is my
major low what is my major high as the
market pushes and breaks structure you
track it down this is my major higher
low and it does not happen it does not
matter what happens within right there
as long as the market stays below this
low right we are still targeting the
high
and I'm gonna show you why this makes
sense a little bit later so there is a
again a price action chart so we don't
have anything right there and what you
can do is you can start drawing support
and resistance
you can start drawing trend lines you
can start drawing uh I don't know you
can put some indicators right there but
again how I believe the market structure
is drawn or how I believe the market
should be traded is like this okay
always Mark your major structure for now
with a with the Thin Line like with a
with the Bold line like this right so
make it both not very thin okay lower
lows and lower highs when the market is
bearish Mark them with a little bit of a
red highlighter when the market is
bullish with blue okay so there's the
breaker structure right there what
caused the break we track the market
back it's this guy we put a red
highlighter right there and then we put
a line here the market broke so again
just before I continue I take Wix as
breaks and I'm gonna explain why a
little bit later
here we break up right
uh we break down actually so here uh you
could have said that this right there
was a liquidity grab because then the
market just Wicked it up and then
continued to break down okay so we have
a new structure break right there what
caused the break we caught we track it
back it's this guy we put this so this
is our Strong high as I'm going to teach
you later the market pulls back brake
structure down cool what caused the
breakout structure track it back is this
guy this guy comes in and breaks so what
do we have right now is a trend change
and then the market shifts uptrend okay
and always see how those harlows are
maintaining like sometimes it can Wick
by a little bit or maybe form equals
that's fine it usually keeps going on
until it shifts and as it shifts we
start making so this is our Strong high
right now push pull back lower high push
pull back this is the last lower high so
we should not break above this one but
we should break the low push pull back
this is the high that shouldn't break
and have a look how perfect it is it
usually it's not supposed to break and
this is why I take Wicks as brakes
because if this level is strong right
there if this level is so strong I don't
want to see it get broken by a wick
because even if it gets taken by a week
then this to me means that okay there
are buyers entering the market they took
out this level so we can eventually
start shifting up and again don't get me
wrong sometimes it happens like here it
happened we Wicked up but then we still
went down here it also happened we just
wake down for a little bit but then the
next candle immediately continues to go
up so you're like okay well this was
just a little bit of a liquidity wrap
right there so this is an example of an
uptrend okay
downtrend
Market structure that is breaking lows
and maintaining the highs so exactly the
opposite in simple terms a market that
is making lower lows and lower highs so
again here the previous and the last
lower low should always break while the
previous High which is the lower high
should not be broken and again to
illustrate it there it is right we have
a high we have a low this low should
always break this high should maintain
we have a low we track it back this is
the lower high this one should hold this
one should break okay and we keep going
on like this until of course we have a
trend change and the market reverses
once again don't get married to these
textbook scenarios right there the
market is usually going to be much more
complex when you put candles on the line
right so it's usually going to look like
this but as I keep saying it's always
important to track back the major lower
high so let's have a look at an example
there is a pretty big one right so you
can actually pause the video right now
pause the video and try to mark it up
right just take a screenshot go market
it up and let's compare later so
here's my markup right so what I just
simply do again is I just follow
structure okay so this is where we broke
we made a new lower low what caused the
brake I track it down this is right
there we have a pullback in my private
program we have very specific rules for
actually identifying the lower highs
because in this case for example here we
push this is the major High it still did
not break have a look how the market
textbook respect to this then came in
respected this right then it broke down
in this case we have to track it back
what caused this break right there
according to me it's this one you might
say it's this one so we might say it's
this one right so again you need rules
what is your lower high according to me
it's this guy we pull back lower high
lower low there is the lower low right
so we know when the lower low has formed
when you have like at least two candles
in the opposite direction
okay and then we track it back there is
the major lower high so this one should
not break the market pulls back makes
another breaker structure right there we
track it back what the most important
question is what caused the breaker
structure you track it back there it is
the market pulls back holds below it
continues to break down here there is a
break of structure it occurred exactly
right there you ask the question what
caused the break okay you can say
according to me it's this one but you
can say it's this one you can say it's
also this one okay this is why again you
need clear rules this one as you can see
got respected the market gave us a
pullback massively dropped another
pullback massively dropped here you can
see the level was invalidated by a very
little Wick so again according to me
this is a reversal and then this to me
turns into the major uh low which is a
higher low so we have a push pullback
push pull back the market try to hold
and what it did is again aligned bearish
on the forge so we have this little
short-term pullback break below again
what caused the break it's this
we track it back the market consolidate
took out the low good what caused this
load to be taken tracking it back it's
this the market came in reacted and
reversed right so then what caused the
reversal what caused this break it's
this low it's not this it's not a valid
range it's this right push and then we
just keep going okay and then you're
gonna have of course you can see the
market is not perfect you have like
ranges right there you have ranges right
there you're gonna have a bullish Market
overall here but you have two very big
ranges but still what is really
important is that you always if you have
this breaker structure right there and
makes a new hard high what is the higher
low that caused the high what caused the
breakup structure they track it back
it's this guy you draw your line and you
can see perfectly doesn't matter what we
do
if we are above this guy we expect the
high to go and I'm gonna tell you why we
do that later
got taken and then we reversed okay so
very nice example this is downtrend
and uh another example for you so again
pause the video and Mark Mark's
structure right there
right so again here
there is your structure so I just went
on and I this is on the uh doe Jones so
this is us-30 I just went on and marked
structure and you can see this one does
not look perfect okay we have a
downtrend we always track what are the
major lower highs here we had a very
little alignment right but you can see
the market made push pull back push pull
back push pull back right so if you are
looking at the market from a macro
perspective as well right you can say ah
this is my lower high this is my lower
low right and then this is my lower high
well usually this is a little bit wrong
it's not wrong right but then you're
missing out on all of these setups right
there all of these setups then you're
missing out on this short term uptrend
right and again what a lot of people
tend to do is of course draw like very
big macro structure like something like
this okay which is again not wrong
because pretty much this is a this is a
full body time frame but on the daily
this is going to be a push this is going
to be a pullback then this is going to
be a daily push and this is going to be
a daily pullback and as you can see here
the forward time frame starts to range
which means that potentially like it's
accumulating for another move okay so
make sure to practice this
the final Market is a consolidating
market which is very tricky and it's
defined as Market structure that is
failing to break both the highs and the
lows or is just throwing Wicks above or
below right
ranges by the way are very important
because this is where the bfis were
cooking this is where they're exchanging
their orders and agreeing to potentially
move the market right so this is where
they decide where they want to go next
all right so I want you to go on your
chart right now and and go and spot like
a very big move somewhere and I promise
you before this big move there is going
to be like a period of a consolidation
right and there is going to be usually a
liquidity wrap so usually what happens
is the market goes from a downtrend and
then starts to range a little bit it
ranges like starts getting a little bit
sloppy and then you have this
okay so what happens right there is the
market is accumulating orders he's
building up orders then there is usually
going to be a liquidity gap which I'm
going to teach you in the supply and
demand video coming up next and then the
market just massively expands
Okay so
pretty much trading within this
consolidation is very risky if you have
a consolidation on the form at a time
frame or in the daily time frame this
can be a trend on the hourly or on the
50 minute but do not trade lower time
frame consolidations why because of this
because above every consolidation there
are people that are looking to go long
and there are stop losses of sellers so
right there we have this beautiful
resistance level right what is above
this resistance level we have people
that are looking to take the breakout
with a buy stop and we have people that
are already short from here and have
their stop loss above okay what do we
have at the downside support level what
is below if we break below a lot of
people are going to be looking to take a
breakout which means they have a sell
stop order and all the people that are
long from here they have their stop loss
okay so I'm going to show you an example
right now
why this is the case
here it is right so again I want you to
go ahead right now and pause this video
and mark the structure again
did you do this
pause the video
I know you're not pausing the video all
right so hopefully you did right so here
you see that when you open this chart
and you let's imagine that this price
action does not exist right there when
you open this chart what is the first
thing that comes to mind okay it's
ranging yes but there is still structure
in between however it's not clean okay
but it's still as I said it's tradable
so this is pretty much a daily
consolidation right there so you can see
the flowery Market tends to change up
and down Wicks down goes up yes this is
a hard low formation right there but
then the market chops again pushes up
high higher low good then Heart High so
you had like a little micro Trend right
there then it shifts down then it shifts
back up again you can see it's overall
like an uptrend and if you again read
Market structure properly you are going
to be entering into those trades okay
and then the market throws this little
big push so again what I tell you guys
before a big move
we have a consolidation we have a nice
buy to trick because what is above this
consolidation there are stop losses of
people that are short and there are buy
stops of people that want to go long
okay so what pretty much happens is this
you have stop losses and buy stops above
you have stop losses and sales stops
below right you can see how many times
so here we had a wick
the market week below the week here we
have a wick the market week below the
wick so what is this doing it's
triggering sellers into the market and
stopping out the buyers right here we
have this big range the market makes a
massive move up and then look at the
expansion lower right and the expansion
guess what
it gives us a beautiful downtrend so
what we simply have to do is wait for
the consolidation to be over wait for
the for the orders to be taken and then
the market is going to create a trend so
this is why patience is key these
consolations you don't want to trade so
this is a very big consolidation and
then we have small consolations in
between this is absolutely unclean so
again if you see price action like this
that is Wiki that is not clean skip it
okay so before we jump on to some
examples and uh
and more advanced Market structure I
want to share some details right Mark
your structural points with a
highlighter too I'm gonna go on the
charts right now and show you detail is
that Wicks are breaks for me but what
you can do is you can do also body
brakes to me body brakes do not work
right because then sometimes you had a
weak break the market just massively
continues while you're still waiting for
your body break okay again according to
me if you have
um
a downtrend and this is your lower high
okay and if the market comes in and just
Wicks above it this to me is a break so
what I'm going to be doing is then this
is my low I'm going to be looking for a
long setup because if this level was so
strong it shouldn't have broken how do
you know if this is going to be a
liquidity graph if the market goes on
and breaks the low and then you can say
okay well we shifted structure up but it
was technically a liquidity drop so what
I'm going to do right now is I'm just
going to continue following the flow
down okay so this is for you to decide
are you going to do bodies or are you
going to do Wicks to me Wicks work great
okay
also a little detail be aware that the
trend is fully established after two
highs or lows are created let me give
you an example okay what tends to happen
sometimes is you have an uptrend
okay so what is the market supposed to
do in this case is maintain this low and
break this high but what happens
sometimes is you have this one break
okay so is this an established downtrend
no this is just showing us a trend
change which I'm gonna teach you a
little bit later in the formations this
is a trend change but what tends to
happen sometimes as I showed you in just
in the previous example with a liquidity
Gap sometimes this happens
okay so when is a trend established is
when you have this
which is a trend change then the market
pulls back does not break Above This
High which is right now a major high and
then breaks the low so what you have
right now is one lower low two lower
lows right so two lows are created in
this example and right now you can say
okay we've made the trend change and we
have confirmed the trend change by a
breakup structure but I'm gonna tell you
I am usually very aggressive with these
setups as well when I have a trend
change this is again this is what people
call charge change of character this is
when the character of the market changes
from bullish to bearish and this is when
you can potentially expect that a
reversal is incoming okay but again a
trend is not established before you have
two of those highs and lows okay
as I taught you in examples always Mark
your structure breaks and always Trail
back price to see where your lower
higher higher low is and again mark it
with a bold line
learn to zoom in on your charts and spot
all the details don't be zooming out
like looking at the market from a macro
perspective you are not like positional
Traders zoom in and look at all the
details
major and swing structure is your main
Trend Guidance Do not confuse it with
minor and substructure we are going to
look at minor and substructure and in
the last list and I'm going to teach you
time frames okay so minor structure
forms within the major one and we're
going to explore that a little bit later
always take note of consolidations and
ranges right do not trade him on a lower
time frame than the one hour at a time
frame it's just not worth it if the
market is consolidating on the following
you're gonna have Trends you're gonna
have 15 minutes you're gonna have one
hourly price action but if the market is
consolidating on the hourly or on the 50
minute do not trade okay
practice practice makes perfect
understanding structure is your first
goal right now as a Trader and then of
course everything else will build up on
top of it okay and of course a gap of
your understanding and structure will
really hinder you from understanding the
advanced concepts later right what I see
a lot of people do is they jump on the
flashy smart money Concepts without
actually understanding structure right
to start drawing supply and demand to
start doing like SMC traps you start
doing order blocks you start doing all
of those stuff
but within the foundation of that stuff
if you really carefully look at it right
it's Market structure unorder block
forms when you have an uptrend and the
market makes a break of structure this
is your higher low information that is
not supposed to break right and this is
where you draw your order block and why
does this hold is because the structure
is bullish and this is the higher load
that should be maintained
okay so it's not like rocket science
it's just Market structure so right now
I just want to go on the charts and show
you a real example so that you actually
know how to practice drawing basic
Market structure all right here we are
on a newer USD chart on the full hourly
time frame once again exactly what I'm
speaking right now is about Trend
identification I identify my trend on
the full hourly time frame this is my
major time frame this is my Trend time
frame okay the 15 minute is my minor
time frame which we're going to cover
later okay so here this is where we Mark
Market structure okay so I just want to
show you the the process so it's not
only like examples on a on the on the
PowerPoint
um let's let's just go back a little bit
like stop somewhere randomly maybe have
a look well let's have a look here I
also want to pick a little bit of a
complex price action so that you
actually learn something and to see how
the market is not very perfect okay so
here let's start from right there okay
so there we had a breaker structure how
I marked by breaking structure is again
I have like you can see here I have a
flowery break that up probably break
down 50 minutes up 50 minute down 50
minute train change five one chain
change liquidity grabs right so you can
copy this right so when I do this
flowerly break up okay so then after
this heart high is formed once again how
do you know that a higher high is formed
well when you have like at least one
pullback candle away okay so this as if
it keeps pushing then it keeps pushing
but when it stops you pretty much see it
you cannot miss it okay so then the
important point to ask is okay what
caused this breaker structure up okay so
from the high you track it back and you
see that it was actually this guy so
what a lot of a lot of you will do is
they're gonna see well it's this one
because this is the lowest point before
the break and this is what I did in the
past but right now I have very specific
rules that are very refined and they
tell me that this is my quality break
right so we here we went so what I'm
gonna do so we had a highlighter too uh
we were bullish har High
Arlo was created so if you just track it
back down this is not valid yeah okay so
the valid one here was this guy okay so
we were this is the Harlow this is the
heart high so we're not supposed to
break below this guy we just gave a
little pullback went on and took out the
high which was supposed to be broken
okay so just that we built a story here
as I tell you again I take Wix as brakes
because if this level was so strong it
shouldn't have Wicked okay so what
happens right now is we have a trend
change on the 4-H and remember a trend
is not established yet but what I
immediately do okay
this is my high that is that was bullish
but right now it's kind of turning
bearish and right now we have a lower
low
this lower low what caused it we track
it back and pretty much it's this guy
there is nothing else so this is our
Strong high right now this one should
hold okay the market pulls back
potentially it forms a lower high and
again I told you the market is not
perfect but what I was supposed to do is
we should be going and taking out the
low the market Consolidated right there
for five days before actually went on
and broke it so what do we have right
now is a new
lower low so how do we know that the
lower low forms so here you have a
bullish candle bearish candle bullish
bullish there it is it's formed right
then you track it back right you track
it back there is the last pullback
before the break okay it's not this it's
not this it's this so this is not
supposed to break
but again as I told you the market moves
in Cycles we had like a little kind of
ABC to the downside and what the market
does it breaks structure up right so
what we have right now is a trend change
to the upside
the market pushes it starts pulling back
perfect what caused this break okay in
this case
it's not this and pretty much
yeah okay so in this case according to
me in this case it's gonna be this guy
okay so this is our strong low right now
so what we have let's let me not forget
so yeah this was a low but right now we
made the high right so what we're
looking for right now is for our Harlow
and what I'm gonna teach you later is
the 50 right which is usually where the
market comes in before making a new high
and here you can see the market makes
all of this stuff so this is minor
structure right now and what it
eventually did is it came in and took
out the high okay what is the structure
what is the low that took out the high
we track it back it's this guy okay so
this is supposed to be our Harlow
formation but what happens is the market
just comes in and breaks it right it
didn't even react it just broke it okay
this happens so what we do is we flow
this is a four hourly breaker structure
down what caused this breaker structure
down it's this okay so this one right
now it's supposed not to break
the market pulls back right and then
what it does is it breaks structure
lower right so you have to be zoomed in
so this is according to me a break it
even broken a body if you wish to see a
body what caused this break you track it
back up it's this guy
so this one is not supposed to break
okay and what you see happen right there
is
the market pulled back right there and
then what it did it took out the low
here technically making a new lower low
which was what we wanted to see and then
immediately breaking it back up okay so
here we have a slightly tricky situation
but this is a bullish reversal so are
you gonna yeah technically it's valid to
Market from here because I'm not sure
what this candle did it first push down
and then broke up or did it first broke
up and then push down nevertheless we
had a couple of lower lows right now we
have a push up okay so what is the
structure that caused this push-up it's
this but like we don't have a new heart
High formed yet there is one bearish
candle no hard height keeps pushing up
here we have one candle only and then
the next candle breaks so this is still
not a Harlow formation this one is okay
so this is where we actually form the
Heart High which was eventually broken
this is the low that is not supposed to
break if you just Mark 50 percent
okay came very very very very very close
and yeah pulls back Harlow breaks the
high you immediately track it what so we
made a new heart High what is the low
that caused the new heart high is this
one right so what we see happen is again
the market does all of this stuff right
there but it stays above our major
Harlow that is this guy and what it
eventually does
breaks the high
cool we have a high bearish candle
bullish in the range bullish in the
range okay we definitely have a new
heart High I forgot to mark my my
structure
right so always make sure to do this
right Mark your structure and be aware
where is your major structure and your
higher lows and lower highs should be
with such a line right there we broke up
what caused the break in this case it's
not this right according to my rules in
fact it's this so after this push the
market is not supposed to be breaking
below here but what the market did is
just gave us a little pullback and kept
on and broke structure okay
this push okay so this is a new higher
high we immediately asked the question
oops
come on okay I want to copy this but I'm
copying better so here what caused this
breakup okay and in this case
um according to my rules yeah it's going
to be this case yeah it's going to be
this guy okay so yeah what the market
does it pulls back and immediately
breaks and here okay here we entered
into a oh I'm not gonna break this down
okay so this is the time guys okay when
we have a consolidation market and
pretty much is this December yeah so
this is pretty much Christmas and you
don't want to be trading okay so I'm
gonna stop here but hopefully it makes
sense right and this works on every
Market if you're trading uh what what
can you be trading if you're trading um
s p Futures right works the same go on
the follow the time frame let's have a
look what is happening
um can we pick a nice one I don't wanna
do we have a bearish example
yeah let's let's do this okay yeah let's
do this for example right there so
from the top right there we had a
breaker structure what caused the break
it was this this one immediately got
broken okay so we got broken right there
and then you ask immediately question
okay what caused the break is this guy
so this is not supposed to break the
market pulls back beautiful massively
drops new brake of structure okay the
market forms a lower low right there
yeah it's not valid though
and but this one is valid okay so here
we have a valid break lower what caused
this lower low is this unfortunately
this one got broken okay so here you
also have to be clear if you have clean
rules this according to me made the new
heart High it pulled back with more than
three candles broke up and then
immediately broke down so then according
to me this is not very clean but it's a
flowery break okay so we shift bearish
the market makes a new lower low what
caused this lower low it's this
so the market pulls back goes on makes a
new lower low
there's the lower low what cause the
lower low you track it back it's this so
the market should not break below it
okay it pulls back roughly 50 breaks the
low okay what caused this lower low
which formed right there
it's this so this one is not supposed to
break and in this case we uh in this
case we Wicked it a little bit yeah
which is fine so yes in this case what
I'm gonna be doing is because I'm very
strict with my rules I'm gonna be saying
well okay this is a quality break but
again just intuitively I am gonna be
aware that this could be a liquidity
grab but still I'm gonna be doing this
so what is what is the the low that
caused the break of this High uh it's
not this unfortunately so it's this
right so what I'm going to be doing is
I'm going to be looking to learn from
here it gave a nice reaction and then it
broke the slow okay so then what caused
the break of the slow it's this this is
what's supposed to be strong okay but
unfortunately it also broke up here we
have a flower we break our highs formed
what caused the Heart High it's this so
this one is not supposed to break and
yeah you just keep going this one is
getting a little bit volatile but
hopefully you get the point okay so
right now I don't want to make this too
long I want you to go in and practice
this and right now after you know how to
Mark a structure how to track back the
major harlows how to mark them I'm gonna
teach you right now some more advanced
concepts which if you put to on top of
what you just learned it's gonna get
much more powerful so let's see
it's time to step it up a notch and
cover some Advanced Market structure
Concepts that are really going to deepen
your understanding of Market structure
you're going to be much more confident
and of course it's going to give you a
little bit more of a Confluence when
you're marking up your structure and
when you're trading okay so the first
concept we're gonna cover is strong and
weak highs and lows and before I really
jump onto all the details this is super
simple okay a Harlow is trunk a heart
high is weak why because a higher high
has to break Harlow has to has to hold
the opposite for a downtrend okay so a
strong high is a high that has broken
structure to the downside and has
created a new confirmed lower low so
basically that's a lower high okay a
strong low is a low that has broken
structure to the upside and has created
a new confirmed car hype so basically
this is a Harlow right a weak low is a
low that has that hasn't caused any
break and shift in structure which is
simply a lower low
right and a weak high is a high that
hasn't caused any break and shifts in
structure simply a car High
okay so we're gonna cover the textbook
examples in a bit but what we want to do
so you might want to review this twice
uh this whole video is we trade against
and away from the strong structure and
we trade towards the weak one okay so
simply guys we buy from harlows and we
target the heart high or we sell from
lower highs and we target the last lower
lows it's that simple all right but what
is the psychology behind is that
a strong structural point which is a
strong high or strong low will cause a
break of previous structure right and
this makes it strong why well it's
probably because the bfis entered from
there and they will likely protect that
high which is why also strong highs and
lows are called protected highs and lows
right so yeah we call them strong
protected right because the bfis will
not allow for price to go above or below
right because they will usually go into
drawdown so again this is just a theory
it's not a fact I don't know if this is
really the case this is what I've
observed and this is what I've learned
Okay so take note of the slide
here is an example okay what it simply
this is is just Market structure
all right
this push calls the break then we have a
pullback so this is not supposed to
break this is protected why well because
the bfis made this footprint this big
push up right so they wouldn't like to
go below their order so it doesn't make
sense for them to go into drawdown right
the market then pushes up causes a break
of structure so remember a strong low or
a higher low is a low that causes a
break of structure okay and this is why
then we draw our bold line right there
this is not supposed to break why
because it's strong why because probably
institutions are entering from here
okay
the market is all the stuff in between
and again the highs they're weak this is
where potentially institutions will be
looking to drive the price to offload
their positions and take profits again
why do you have a pullback so you have
an uptrend right so why do you always
have a pullback when a new hire high is
made because they take profit on top
right so they bought from here they
pushed up they're taking profits right
there this is why the market goes down
this is where they enter again right
just above the strong the strong low
they push the market up take profits
then they go again okay so again the
market moves in cycles and exactly the
same thing as when a downtrend okay the
lower high is always going to be strong
strong strong
and we always trade towards the weak
ones all right so this is also called
expectational order flow because you
expect that this overall order flow this
overall bullish Market structure will
continue going and again the highs are
always going to be taken until they are
not right and this is when you have this
okay the market pushes up this is
potentially a strong low but what you
start seeing is that the market is kind
of giving us a little bit of a shift
there is a little bit of a bearish
market structure coming in right there
but again what really matters is where
is your strong one so as long as the
strong one stays in intact right you
keep long but this could be a reversal
sign right there if you really start
seeing the market going down and
starting to break structure against you
and really trending down then it should
start being aware that it might
potentially start burning up new strong
Highs coming from the top and then
eventually break your your major strong
low okay so this is just a little bit of
a detail right when the market fails to
break uh the weak High okay so here you
can see the market massively breaks
lower makes in fact a weak low but then
it starts to shift it starts building a
beautiful Market structure to the upside
on the floor time frame and then if this
one fails a very big detail is is that
when the first strong low fails you
don't care about the rest all of them
are are going to get taken so the market
is going to take them all as liquidity
because right now who is in control
it's the sellers in this case and in
this case it's going to be the buyers so
be aware of these situations right not
always a week low is going to get taken
okay
there's an example
right so I want you to again pause this
video mark up your structure and mark up
also the strong and weak highs and lows
did you do that pause
all right hopefully you paused
there it is for me right this is the 15
minutes right this is the 15 minute so
again
check it out okay check out how I Mark
the structure check out the strong hives
which is simply the lower highs spot
right there how this was a strong high
but it turned into weak right so we have
a trend change the market made a new
high we track it backward is a strong
one it's this never broke and then we
start moving up and up and up a little
bearish alignment right there so this
turns into strong the market pulls back
lower high lower low but then we have a
TC okay so then we start pushing him so
study this example carefully
right
there's another one again I want you to
pause the video now mark it up again
spend some time right if you're not
willing to spend some time with me to to
markup structure you're not gonna get it
so pause
there it is right so take a note of this
right so we have the breaker structure
up the breaker structure and in this
case I'm doing exactly the same that I
did previously but we just build it up
on that concept that the higher lows are
also strong lows and they're supposed to
be protected and if a strong low fails
right as you can see in this case right
there we have the
where's my mouse we had like a little
bit of a chop right there but those are
valid harlows right the first strong
long failed this one is gonna fail this
one is gonna fail and this one is gonna
fail
right the cap is like a chain reaction
this is why the most recent one is the
most important
okay so hopefully it makes sense right
now
the big problem for all of you major
minor structure what's that okay super
simple the main determinant of major
Manu structure are time frames it's so
simple okay so remember price is the
same but time frames are just a
different representation of price
providing either less or more details
okay so what you have is the hard time
frames which you're providing with your
major your swing your confirmed Market
structure your strong structure right
this is on your hard time frame and to
me as I told you in my examples before
this is the flowery time frame for you
it could be the daily for others it
could be the one hourly time frame the
market is fractal which means that the
same patterns the same Market structure
the same stuff is going to be repeated
across all the time frames okay so if
you have your major structure on your
hard time frame which is on the footage
respectively the lower one you choose is
going to be your minor it's going to be
your internal structure is going to be
your complex structure this is what we
find on our middle time frames which for
me my middle time frame is the 15 minute
so I go from the 4H to the 15 minute so
this is the most important transition
transitioning from the forwarded time
frame to the 50 minute and then if you
want to do another one for entries from
the 50 minute to the one minute but it's
all the same it's fractal right
if your hard time frame is the is the 50
minute
right and then your middle time frame
could be I don't know maybe the the
three minute or the five minute right
and then your entry could be the one
minute so I usually recommend having
three time frames and I'm gonna teach
you that later
okay so as I keep saying structure is
literally everywhere right but what
makes a huge difference is knowing what
to look for and on which time frames
right it's not like it's it's very
complex you just gotta be systematic
with your time frames knowing where is
your major structure knowing where is
your minor structure okay so it's very
important that you understand first of
all hard time frame Direction which we
just covered in major structure and then
start trading uh the major structure but
zoom in on the minor one and then we can
take counter Trends and pro Trends let's
examine see how this is what this one is
done okay so what is like you might ask
why is a complex pullback and a
correction this is just a minor
structure within a major lick
okay so if I just give you an example
there it is this guy right there so the
blue and the red are the flaw at the
time this is the hard time frame okay so
we have a push on the hard time frame we
have a pullback on a hard time frame and
we have a push and a hard time frame
okay
then the the the the black one is how
the lower time frame so how the 50
minute is going to look like in this
case right and the 50 minute is gonna be
doing this and what is this this is your
internal structure okay how do you know
that a heart high is formed is when you
have a 50 minute Trend change down okay
and then you start marking up again
right so strong High break Strong high
break right break again Strong high
until we shift up and that is when we
start the push phase
okay so this is just a very simple
example there is a little bit more okay
so I want you to screenshot this chart
and study it right so study it I'm not
going to cover it in Great details
because I just showed you right again uh
for you uh the black line in this case
is the major structure that could be uh
the daily or it could be the voyage
right but if the the black line is the
daily then the two other colors is going
to be the quality time frame right or if
you have the flow at the time from is
your major then the 50 minutes is going
to be your minor you choose okay so as I
told you the market moves in Cycles it
pushes up
it becomes expensive there is a hard
time frame Supply that gives you the
reaction the market goes down okay where
does it go to the major higher low what
is this it's the strong low on the
forage that is not supposed to break
right so then what do you have is just
following the 50 minute okay so there is
the trend change so the market goes up
you go long long long long higher highs
formed and then usually also a little
detail how do you know that a heart high
is formed on the four hourly is when you
have a 50 minute Trend change or touch
as some call it
gives us a trend pull back lower high
lower low lower high lower low lower
high lower low Taps into demand which is
also very close to the strong low on the
voyage right shifts the 50 minute Trend
change so then as I told you
respectively all of these highs will
fail and where are we gonna go we're
gonna go towards the weak high on the
voyage
right and then you just continue marking
your 50 minute structure up and up and
up and up
so screenshot this slide study it and if
you just add what we just learned which
is strong lows and strong highs there it
is exactly the same thing repeats on the
15 minute time frame we just gotta be
aware that again the black line is the
voyage this is our flowery major Harlow
which is strong this is our flowery
major High which is weak right the
market pulls back comes very close to
our major Harlow okay and you can see
here on the 50 minute push strong low
brake of structure strong low break of
structure strong low brake of structure
here that was supposed to be strong but
it broke so we have a trend change and
then we turn bearish Strong high pulls
back Strong high here pulls back Strong
high we shift up and then respectively
all of these are gonna fail and then
what we just do is follow the 50 minute
Trend all the way until the four hourly
time frame takes out the high and then
exactly the same thing repeats over and
over again
okay so this is it this is the answer
it's within how you transition between
different time frames so if the
following time frame is is this right
the 50 minute time frame is going to be
looking like that always
and right now I'm going to show you an
example on how to practice this okay so
what I want you to do is go on a full
hourly chart right now if you decide
that your flow at the time frame is your
major time frame and just Mark structure
okay so here we have a massive drop what
caused this drop we track it all the way
back up it's actually this guy is the
Strong high right the market then pulls
back lower low comes in makes a new
lower low okay what caused this lower
low is this which actually got broken
cool it got broken what caused the break
it's this it makes a new heart High what
caused the break it's this high
Harlow push breaks what caused the break
it's this right so what then you do is
you take again this black line that I
showed you and you take it from every
high and every low and you just link
them like this okay and then what you
have to do this is where the key comes
in is you go to the 50 minute time frame
but you keep the black line and it's
going to look like this
right and this is your minor structure
this is where we broke structure on the
4-H
right how do you know that the heart
high is formed the 50-minute structure
changes there is your 50 minute pullback
you can go short this is where the 50
minute aligned bullish right this is
where you go all the way Longs okay this
is where the market broke forward
structure up it continues to go up until
it changes on the 15 minute here like it
didn't change for the first time it
changed for a little bit came and took
it out again then it shifted again right
and it just keeps going
right so then this is our major flower
Harlow this is potentially the Heart
High that is supposed to be broken right
the market pulls back right there aligns
bullish and then what do we target we
target the Valley High there it is but
again in between the black lines you're
gonna have lots of structure and this is
where the strategy comes in right this
is where you actually trade within the
four hourly time frame within the major
structure which you execute on the minor
one so again I want you to go on right
now and do this exercise in fact I'm
just going to go on my chart right now
and just show you one example because
this lesson is getting a little bit
longer so let's do that
all right so here I am in a gold chart I
know a lot of you trade gold so let's
have a look at Goat right I'm just gonna
start from right here right and again I
want to do exactly the same that we did
um in the previous chart example right
for the breaker structure what caused
the break it's this okay continuous
flowery so mark all of this up I am not
gonna mark it I'm just gonna show you
how to do major in minor you go here and
you find the PATH too okay click on it
and after all of your markups are done
and also make sure to do it with uh with
the highlighter right so push pull back
push pull back
right so there it is but I want you to
not to make it like me so mark it with
the strong lows strong highs do
everything okay so then what you do is
you mark the as you get the
where did it go
uh uh where are you passed so you find
the path to I kind of lost it okay there
it is so here you find the path to and
then you simply link all of the all of
your highlighter uh little dots okay so
we start from here
boom boom boom boom boom so what this
does right now for you is it marks your
four hourly
major structure
okay
so then you do this right so I'm doing
it way too much you don't want to do it
with so much like uh price action you
usually what you want to do is just
examine one single leg like let's see in
this example I just want to examine this
this push and this pullback okay so
after you have this you make it a little
bit Bolder right and then what you
simply do
15 minutes
right and there it is as I said like
then you can go on and you can say okay
I'm going to examine this right so there
is the push there is the push okay so
then you drop there is my first 50
minute Trend change right there so what
you start doing right here is again have
a look how you can trade this right and
then you do exactly the same thing that
you did on the 4-H but on the 15 minute
hi Harlow our high Harlow are high
Harlow our life so here we broke up down
right and then you you just do all of
that stuff okay but again you also have
to be aware where are we on the footage
right so example
for example here if this is my strong
low right and this is my weak high again
what I'm just going to teach you right
now is the 50 so the market gets below
50 right but before that the 50 minute
right the 50 minute kind of gave us a
bearish shift here uh but yeah then go
out on the 50 minute I don't really
trade gold in the 50 minute it looks
quite mad but here you had a break up
right so you can take a long here our
high our low our high this is where we
shift it down so uh lower low
yeah what caused this lower low it looks
like yeah it looks like it's still this
lower high lower low this is where the
the 50 minute aligned bullish right so
for the first time and then you have
higher high high low higher high low
high high low and this is how you trade
it on the way up towards the week high
okay and then you find the other one so
there it is Harlow har hi what happened
right so this is where we pulled back
okay this is where uh this is where for
example the market aligns bullish how
can you get long
right so har hi Harlow har High Harlow
High Harlow right there then we aligned
a little bit bearish we just came in to
retest the area the market came in
aligns bullish again and there you start
again high high Harlow high high Harlow
again you can see how the strong low
never broken and then you go on and make
a new heart high right so that's the
secret and that's the exercise if you do
this enough you're gonna Master it I
promise okay so once again follow the
time frame Mark all of your Market
structure diligently first with all the
stuff that you can do and then you just
simply go on the following time frame
and you take it leg by leg right so in
this case we have this push and we have
this pullback okay so you go in okay how
did the push happened
right so the push aligned bearish right
there so how can I take a short rate on
the push right and then start marking
structure well there's my lower high
there's my lower low I can take a short
from here
right what is my major lower high in
this case it's this guy take a short
from here came in didn't break it take a
shirt from here here we broke it what
caused this break right
it's this little guy there's another
short there is another break what caused
this break it's this there is another
short right there then we break and here
we actually form the lower low right so
then the market aligns bullish right
there can I take a loan from here yes
this is my pullback trade right then
start Harlow Harlow hard high right then
you just do this over and over again
enough times you're gonna Master major
and Market structure the biggest key for
you right now is to decide what is your
major what is your minor if you want to
follow me my major is the voyage my
matter is the 15 minute and then what I
do is when I mark up my minor structure
right and then I say for example okay
if I just delete everything uh this is
where the 50 minute created a trend
change right then this is my demand zone
so what I'm going to be doing right here
is I'm going to be dropping to the one
minute time frame and doing exact same
thing with a couple of more details okay
so I'm going to be looking for here for
the one minute time frame to align and
then I'm gonna be looking for a long
setup okay so for me it's a three step
down process okay so do this exercise
right now back into the final Advanced
Market structure concept
a very huge part of my trading strategy
is drawing trading ranges right so
what's that well pretty much you know
the concept of trading is to always buy
low and sell high right and drawing a PD
range which is a premium and discount
range exactly helps us with that right
because as I told you in the beginning
the market goes from expensive to cheap
and vice versa from cheap to expensive
and again our aim is to know what is
cheap so we can buy it and what is
expensive so we can sell it right so we
buy low and sell high and this is uh I
think it's best done with trading ranges
of course you can do it with indicators
oversold overbought but against me price
is what it's gonna tell you if it's
cheap or it's expensive trading ranges
exist on every time frame from the
monthly to the one minute it's the
fractal nature of the market right and
everything that happens on one time
frame the same thing is gonna happen on
another one right again as I keep saying
you really have to get clear on what are
your time frames so where are you going
to be drawing the ranges okay what I
usually do is I do follow your ranges
absolutely always and then I'm always
going to be aware of the daily ranges
because what happens sometimes is like
um you have
the forward going down and you have the
market probably going up right and then
the market all of a sudden does this
okay and then you're like okay well the
40 time frame was beautifully moving up
so why did it go down well it's because
the daily time frame had a strong High a
weak low and it pulled back into 50 on
the daily and then the fall time from
just plummets okay so if you ever get
like a stop loss or a wrong direction
then go to an upward time frame and
you're gonna find your answer right so
this concept of the PD ranges can be
utilized on every time frame right
uh in order to increase probability
significantly okay I use it also on the
50 minute time frame always okay so
again remember hard time frame will
always Trump the lower ones so flower
ranges will always Trump over the 50
minute ones daily ranges will always
Trump the party ones the weaker ranges
the daily and the monthly ranges the
weekly right it's like a chain reaction
okay
a very important thing to note is that
specific instruments do not pull back
often to equilibrium which is the 50 of
the range right so they are very
momentous so you have to know your Pairs
and know that some pairs for example
like gold like uh volatile pairs like
gjs sometimes as well they just go on
and push and they do not pull back at 50
they usually do around 30 pullbacks okay
how do we draw PD ranges very simple we
use the Fibonacci 2 and we remove
everything else we just keep one 0.5 and
-1 starts on the fifth keep it clean
this is how it looks like and this is
how you do it okay so you open like the
FIB retracement on trading View and you
do exactly the same stats that I have
right there just 0 1 and 0.50 that's it
right in the middle you're gonna have
your equilibrium this is the balance
this is where the market eventually
tries to go right and then to
potentially get into uh expensive price
and go cheap right so you can look at it
at both ways the market can push up oops
just run into the examples let me grab
my pen so while the market does it
pushes up right
then it starts pushing down Taps the
equilibrium gets lower gets into
discount right and then from here we go
on to the weak High okay or what you can
also do is you can have a push the
market right now is cheap so the 50
minute shifts it starts buying buying
buying until it gets to 50 and above and
then usually you're going to see the
market shift down and go and attack the
weak low okay
that's pretty much the concept and it's
very easy if you understood structure so
far you are going to understand the PD
ranges okay there they are what I simply
did right there is I went on and I
marked all the major structure right and
I just drew also the PD ranges and what
you're usually gonna see is again if you
have a push here the market comes in top
50 percent goes here we have a trend
change down the market pulls back 50
goes push down 50 goals here we have a
reversal pulls back to 50 goes reversal
down 50 goes right above 50 goes right
so just examine again pause this video
examine the example it's very nice again
not always look in this case here we
broke up and the market pulled back just
a little bit about 50 it's not perfect
but then the next time we just touch 50
and we explode it right so always be
aware the market is not perfect there is
another good example right you can see
how the market is beautifully moving up
up and up and up and up and then it just
goes down and down and down and down and
just keeps getting to the 50 right so 50
here 50 almost right there above 50 here
it didn't tap right there but then the
next one tapped tapped tapped right it
just keeps going on once again go back
learn how to identify the first lesson
of this video which is just Market
structure and then everything that I
teach you right now is gonna fall into
place so again make sure to go on your
charts and also practice video ranges
together with major in Market structure
okay because again while as this heart
high is formed
you draw the PD range you expect the
markets that 50 and if on the 15 minute
right there you get your minor structure
that is bearish you can take cells until
the 50 and as the 50 Taps then you can
expect that the market is going to turn
bullish and go attack the weak high
right so this is a complete strategy by
itself
let's now explore Market formations
we're almost to the end so stick with me
right so what are the most important
formations you should know about guys
you're not going to believe me this is
very simple okay so Market structure
forms different Market formations right
so those formations have been built and
recognized over time by Traders and
supposedly they provide us with a higher
probability of success right but I think
this is debatable because if the BFI
knows that these formations work well
they they can just manipulate them right
so should we trust them not really right
so there are numerous formations out
there right and we are not going to
cover any of them why because remember
that market formation is informed by
structure itself so if you understand
structure this is all you need right you
don't need this you don't need triangles
channels raising wedges Flags double
tapsible bottoms inverse getting
shoulders no it's all Market structure
right
you just don't need those right you
don't need these like pendants and stuff
and all of that stuff
I promise you guys you don't need those
so
do this actually work yes they do right
this is why they're here because they
work right but do you really need them
uh to study them totally well not really
right again you can see diamonds uh
bottoms Diamond tops uh measure down
move not really the key is within Market
structure
okay so we're not going to be covering
those there are some other things you
might ask me about what about spawn
resistance I think this is subjective
it's manipulated it can be drawn
everywhere leaving you with 100 lines
and you don't know which line to trade
right it can be systematized for a
strategy once again Basics upon
resistance strategy that you execute
over and over again is gonna work long
term okay if you combine it also with
Market structure trend lines I hate
trend lines very subjective they're
manipulated a lot they cannot be
systematized because you can draw one
time frame in a hundred different ways
right triangles channels wages and other
shapes uh good to be aware of them and
to know their meaning because a lot of
times those are utilized for liquidity
right like you have a push
and you have a channel
what is this this is a strong low this
is a weak High what should happen the
market should go up there is 50 the
market has 50 but then what it does like
breaks down breaks up right and then it
does some funky stuff and then it goes
right so your channel and which
formation is completely destroyed but
what is not destroyed is Market
structure the market is still going to
follow the order flow and Market
structure okay so be aware of those but
keep in mind that there are always
manipulated
Head and Shoulders uh favorite formation
of everyone it is just a simple Trend
change or a market structure ship which
I'm gonna tell you right now okay and
this is also manipulated a lot there are
like three ways of markets of Head and
Shoulder formations you don't want to
make it too complicated okay there are
the three formations you have to know
Market structure shift Trend change and
structure breaks right
what is a market structure shift this is
when the market fails to make a new car
high and starts going down right or
fails to make a new lower low and starts
going up so this is your first sign that
a potentially a shift can be occurring
however as I told you where is yours I
want you to pause this video and tell me
where is the Strong high and low in both
of these examples
so hopefully say it's this one and in
this case it's that one why because this
is the low that caused the break of the
high okay this is not structure yet of a
structure is formed if it breaks the
high
okay so MSS Market structure shift shows
us that there is a potential sign of
reversal if this occurs in a high
probability supply and demand Zone on
the left then you could know that
potentially the market can reverse
however there is a it's not very high
probability
right because as I told you this the
major Harlow and lower high are still
intact and this is what usually happens
right there is a bullish example there
it is okay so if you trade MSS which I
do not trade nowadays is again because
as I told you if this is your major
higher low this is supposed to hold and
even though the market gives you a shift
this is all just internal bearish Market
structure tabs the demand Zone and it
just forgets about you right but again
sometimes as I told you this could be a
first sign of the market potentially
reversing it's much better to wait for a
trend change which we're going to cover
next okay here is an example of a market
structure shift uh that was not uh valid
right so the market pushed in it pulled
back for a new higher low then tried to
push and it failed so what this usually
means to me I'm gonna teach about
liquidity in another lesson is that this
low
fails to make a new high so it's weak
right a strong low is a low that caused
the break of the high did the slow cause
the break of the high no so it's
technically weak what the market does
comes in takes it as liquidity and Taps
into our major Harlow and guess what
happens next we go towards the weak High
right
there's another example right there so
the market hasn't yet made a trend
change but it made the shift formation
right there right so then it ended up
pushing up our highs higher highs right
there so here the market was again
bearish because it shifted bearish right
there okay but it failed to take out the
low Right and started making a shift
okay so shift right there as well do we
have any others not really okay so the
shift formation it's not very high
probability there is another one so
again the market was too bullish coming
in from here the market pulled back all
the way down tried to push failed and
try to push again and fail to take out
the high and then in this case an okay
well it's failing to take out the high
it's making an MSS right so maybe we go
down and then you can see respectively
the market goes down but you should not
try to you should not try to forecast
the MSS please wait for your Trend
change there is My Strong high that
shouldn't be broken right now because
this is what caused the break of this
major low right and there is your trade
right there
here again massive breakdown okay the
market tries to pull back fails then
tries to pull back again and then fails
to push MSS but again what happens at
the end Trend change right but then it
just explored it didn't give it as an
entry okay so it's always good to be
aware right of the MSS right but again
it's not very high probability and it's
much better that you wait for a trend
change
okay so there is our Trend change okay
so this pretty much signifies the first
change of the trend right again remember
that in the beginning I told you it
takes two highs or two lower lows to
confirm a trend right so in an uptrend
it is the break of the last major Harlow
right so this is the last push this is
the last major Harlow if we break below
the major high low Trend change right in
a downtrend the market broke structure
down right there what caused the break
it's this as this one breaks Trend
change right again body close or Wix
breaks I take Wicks as I touched before
but you can also use body brakes above
and below structure okay so very simple
and I'm sure by now you know train
changes if you if you've been watching
my videos so weekly Outlook and setups
you know what I talk about there is some
examples okay so what we do right now is
we mainly Mark the TCS right and also
the structure breaks so have a look at
this example right this is where we
broke up what caused the breakup it's
this I think we actually examined this
example uh in today's video yeah this is
your USD right train change down pulls
back lower high breaks down train change
up right train change down Trend change
up you gotta be following those
finally
structure break right this is very
stupid but again this is one of the most
important formations that you should be
uh taking note of is your structure
break right it signifies a break of the
last hour high or the last lower low
right so if there is a structure break
then you have confirmed structure right
and then respectively the higher low
becomes weak
um structure break occurs in already
trending markets after the initial TC or
Market structure shift okay and pretty
much the structure breaks show you the
intention that the market is continuing
in the desired direction right so then
we have here we have a structure
breakdown structure breakdown there we
have a trend change right and then if
the market continues to break up you
have structure break you don't have
Trend changes anymore a train change
happens only once and then the structure
breaks can continue for a while here
we have the major Harlow
I give you a little example right there
with a shift so the market pulled back
below 50 it tried to push it fails then
this one breaks cool this is internal
break
why is this internal break because it's
still staying above the major Harlow
right there but again you can see it
made one break two break it's starting
to build a little bit of supply and then
eventually it breaks Trend change right
and then we continue with structure
breaks and what I always want you to do
is to mark your structure breaks don't
skip them because if you sometimes skip
marking a structure break like this like
I do right there you're gonna miss all
the details and while little structure
break one little Trend change can make
or break okay
so believe me or not those are the three
formations I use in my training that's
it and actually two train change and
structure break all right simple as that
so
we're gonna be wrapping it up some
details always build a story right when
you open your chart it's all confusing
you see lots of things take your time
analyze the major structure mark it up
Mark your uh harlows and heart highs
marker strong structure Mark your PD
ranges and build a story right and with
time you can just make your analysis in
under two minutes personally when I look
at the charts it takes me like uh 30
seconds to have a look at what is
happening okay you will also see TCS
everywhere r-a-o-eco nope we are only
looking for Trend changes at supply and
demand zones and potential harlows and
heart highs or highs and lower lows for
counter Trends okay so so say you have a
push
right an important Trend change is going
to happen if there is a supply on the
left and you have a 50 minute train
change what does that signify is that
you have a potential reversal right but
then if you have a train change right
there in the middle of nowhere it's not
important why because still the market
hasn't up 50 and it hasn't tapped a
demand level
right so again Trend changes are always
seen at potential higher lows and higher
highs or potential higher highs and
lower lows okay so if the market is
potentially making a flowery Harlow it's
below the 50 it's tapping a Zone and if
you get a train change right there oh
very good that's a strong one if the
market pushes up and gives you a change
train change at the top okay car High
could be formed okay so don't look at
train changes absolutely everywhere all
right and again the higher the time
frame the stronger the trend change okay
so each Trend change has a task on each
time frame a trend change on the flow of
the time frame is going to determine
your direction a TC on the 50 minute is
going to determine your Market structure
and a TC on the one minute is going to
give you your entry again the market is
fractal and everything that happens in
one time frame repeats on the other
right so
up next we have how to master supply and
demand training plus a lesson on
liquidity
hopefully you enjoyed it let me know in
the comments if you did are you
overwhelmed if you are you have to
re-watch it one two three four times
five times the more you watch it the
better it's gonna be please go on
practice have a look at my examples
pause them draw the market structure
yourself go on your charts practice
marking up the structure practice major
minor structure practice the PD ranges
right practice the trend changes the
structure breaks and everything that I
taught in this video right because this
really builds up the foundation for
jumping on to the next lesson which is
going to be on supply and demand but you
cannot learn supply and demand you
cannot learn liquidity without mastering
Market structure first so Fanatics I
hope this lesson was insightful let me
know in the comments if it was leave a
like and let me know if you're excited
for the next lesson
foreign